this is the first video in a three-part
series on eating oatmeal to treat
diabetes
up until the development of insulin
doctors were treating diabetes with high
carb diets I've previously reported on
the impact of plant-based seating for
type 2 diabetes but check out this
research on oatmeal diets
[Music]
before there was insulin there was
oatmeal before the discovery vinsulin
the life of many diabetics was saved or
prolonged by Carl Von norden's oatmeal
diet which apparently stumbled upon
accidentally some of his diabetic
patients had GI issues so he put them on
oatmeal and instead of the sugar
spilling over into their urine getting
worse they started getting better he
published his findings in 1903 which was
received with a great deal of skepticism
but the Skeptics were overcome however
in the following years by the weight of
the evidence
a turning point came when a doctor as
notable as James B Herrick gave it a try
Dr Herrick is a claim for his
description of sickle cell anemia which
was originally known as herrick's
syndrome when Dr Herrick began to try
out the oatmeal died on his patients he
was very skeptical but was astonished by
the result intense skepticism was how
Herrick put it his first experience in
prescribing it was far from encouraging
after taking one or two meals the
patient said Doctor I will die before I
taste another spoonful of that oatmeal
mush
and indeed tragically she did
other doctors echoed patient reticence
to tolerate so monotonous and equine
diet but in general Herrick said he went
on to experience little difficulty in
putting patients on the oatmeal diet and
keeping them there for a few weeks and
nothing he reported was more surprising
or more gratifying than the salutatory
effects he witnessed of the oatmeal diet
and diabetes of the young leading to the
1909 Proclamation that no case of
juvenile or adolescent diabetes should
be deprived of the benefits of the
oatmeal cure
the great Elliot Joslin founder of the
oldest and largest diabetes clinic in
the world described the effects of the
oatmeal as sometimes magical describing
the oatmeal cure as an unsolved mystery
referred to back then as one of the
greatest puzzles in diabetes
they did have some Clues though they
found that animal protein had to be
strictly excluded as it annihilates the
favorable action of oatmeal type diets
they used to use eggs with the oatmeal
diet but they got better results without
them and now we know over a century
later that indeed animal protein intake
intensifies insulin resistance which is
the cause of pre-diabetes and type 2
diabetes whereas plant-based Foods
enhance insulin sensitivity which is the
opposite animal protein intake is not
just associated with insulin resistance
and a clear association with an
increased risk of type 2 diabetes and
this included animal protein from meat
Dairy and fish higher insulin resistance
and risk of pre-diabetes and type 2
diabetes but not just an association you
can put it to the test swapping in beans
for beef improves cardio metabolic risk
factors and it doesn't take much replace
just two servings of red meat with
lentils chickpeas split peas or beans a
few days a week and you can
significantly improve fasting blood
sugars and insulin levels along with the
improvements you'd expect like lowering
of cholesterol and triglycerides
based on over a dozen randomized control
trials even just swapping like a third
of protein from animal to plant sources
can significantly improve blood sugar
control what's the difference between
animal protein and plant protein we
think it's the branched chain amino
acids concentrated in animal protein how
do we know branched chain amino acids
are playing a role because if you give
vegans branched chain amino acid
supplements you can make them as insulin
resistant as meat eaters their insulin
sensitivity dropped to the level
resembling omnivores and only improved
again after stopping the supplements
but wait a second I thought insulin
resistance stems from excess
accumulation of fat inside your muscle
cells particularly saturated fat insulin
resistance directly correlates with
increased saturated fat inside your
muscles I've got tons of videos on this
but basically you can show a substantial
and consistent impairment of insulin
action substantial and consistent
insulin resistance after just a single
day consuming a diet high in saturated
fat in fact even a single meal rich in
saturated fat reduces insulin
sensitivity a single dose of butter for
example impairs insulin sensitivity even
in healthy subjects and over time
reducing cholesterol and fat intakes may
even enhance the ability of your
pancreas to pump out insulin in the
first place now the saturated effect
getting lodged in your muscles may come
from the foods going to your mouth or if
you have excess abdominal fat from
previous meals spilling over into your
bloodstream but either way what does
animal protein have to do with it it
turns out a branched chain amino acid
breakdown product appears to stimulate
fat uptake and accumulation inside the
muscle cells but oatmeal doesn't have
any saturated animal fat or animal
protein okay but neither does any plant
food why might oatmeal work particularly
well that's the question I explore next
[Music]
okay
thank you